Office of Equal Opportunity Records UA057
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Office of Equal Opportunity Records
1969 -- 1978
1960 -- 2012
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Miller, Russell E.
Office of Equal Opportunity and Affirmative Action
Executive Director, Office of Institutional Diversity
Office of Institutional Diversity
Equal Education Opportunity Committee (AS&E Faculty)
Equal Education Opportunity Committee (School of Dental Medicine Faculty)
UA057
6.4 Linear Feet 6 boxes
1 Digital Object(s)
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series: Administrative files; Affirmative Action Plans, policies, and reports; Publications; and Unprocessed accessions.
Custodial History
This collection was at least partially created by Russell Miller, so the material's original order and provenance is unknown.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the creation and early years of the Office of Equal Opportunity and Affirmative Action (OEO) at Tufts University in the early 1970s. The office was first known as the Office of Equal Opportunity and Intergroup Relations and then as the Office of Equal Opportunity.
Materials include correspondence, internal reports, affirmative action plans, diversity statistics, and recruitment plans. Some materials also document legal cases and Tufts' compliance with government regulations. Also included are copies of Tufts University's affirmative action plans, policies, and reports from the early 1970s through the 1980s. There is a small amount of material published by the OEO, primarily from the 1980s and 90s. Some material relates to affirmative action-type programs planned by Tufts in the early 1960s before the formal establishment of the OEO.
Related Materials
UA045, Office of the Dean of Arts, Sciences, and Engineering records, DCA
UA015, Fletcher School records, DCA
UA001, Office of the President records, DCA
Biographical / Historical
The Office of Equal Opportunity and Affirmative Action was founded at Tufts University under the auspices of the Office of the President. The initial focus was on providing educational opportunities for African Americans but by the end of the decade the University began to formally promote affirmative action and expand recruitment policies. Some time around 1971, Tufts created the Office of Equal Opportunity and Intergroup Relations under the auspices of the Office of the President. The office was responsible for assuring that Tufts complied with all state and federal regulations, including the creation of formal Affirmative Action plans, as well as working with colleges and departments to oversee recruitment of women and people of color. The affirmative action policies were also expanded to include not only students, faculty, and staff, but vendors and businesses affiliated with Tufts. The office also worked closely with President Hallowell who established the President's Council for Women and Minorities. Around 1980, the office shortened its name to the Office of Equal Opportunity.
The office is currently called the Office of Equal Opportunity and Affirmative Action.
Conditions Governing Access
University records are closed for 20 years from the date of their creation. Records older than 20 years that do not pertain to student education, staff and faculty employment and Board of Trustees records are open for research. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Employment and Human Resources; Admissions and Recruitment; Legal and Regulatory
- Administrative Files, 1963 -- 1989; 1971 -- 1977; UA057.001; 1.2 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists primarily of administrative material from the early years of the Office of Equal Opportunity and Affirmative Action. Materials include extensive correspondence, as well as drafts of affirmative action plans, information about compliance with federal laws, press releases and clippings, and faculty and staff hiring and recruitment.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Folder 3 Administration: Equal Opportunity, Office of, 1973 -- 1976; UA057.001.001.00001 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
    Office of Equal Opportunity and Affirmative Action
  - Folder 5 Administration: Equal Opportunity, Office of (Affirmative Action), 1971 -- 1974; UA057.001.001.00002 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - [Civil Rights Act Compliance], 1978; UA057.001.001.00003 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Folder 2 Administration: Equal Opportunity, Office of (Correspondence), 1963 -- 1965; UA057.001.001.00004 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Folder 4 Administration: Equal Opportunity, Office of (Faculty Recruitment Procedure), 1977; UA057.001.001.00005 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Faculty & Staff: University Affirmative Action, 1971; UA057.001.001.00006 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Faculty & Staff: University Affirmative Action Plan, 1974; UA057.001.001.00007 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Faculty & Staff: University EEO Counts, 1981; UA057.001.001.00008 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Folder 6 - Equal Opportunity (Affirmative Action) Newsclippings and PR Releases, 1969 -- 1989; UA057.001.001.00009 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - [Search for Health Sciences Vice-President and the Fletcher School Dean], 1977 -- 1983; UA057.001.001.00010 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
    CROSS REFERENCES: Information on the search for the Health Sciences Vice-President (who reported to the University President) is cross-listed with Jean Mayer's papers in UA001/013. Information on the search for the Dean of the Fletcher School is cross-listed with the records of the Fletcher School in UA015/004.
- Affirmative Action Plans, Policies, and Reports, 1960 -- 2006; 1972 -- 1978; UA057.002; 4.8 Linear Feet
  This series consists of Affirmative Action plans, reports, and policies created by Tufts University. Generally, the reports include statistical reports and policies submitted by each college or department, information regarding staff and faculty recruitment procedures, university statistics, student information, and proposed changes to affirmative action policies. In addition to single volume reports, the bulk of the series consists of two different, multivolume plans, created in 1975 and 1978, respectively.
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  20 years from date of creation. Open for research.
  - Equal Employment Opportunity Compliance Regulations, 1960; UA057.002.001.00011 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
    Date is approximate
  - Tufts University's Affirmative Action Program for Progress, 1971; UA057.002.001.00012 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Tufts University Supplementary Statistics: Annual H.E.W. Report, 1972; UA057.002.001.00013 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Women at Tufts University: A Preliminary Inquiry, 1972; UA057.002.001.00014 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Administration - Equal Opportunity, Office of: Affirmative Action Plan, 1974; UA057.002.001.00015 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Personnel, 1975; UA057.002.001.00016 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
    Contains various Affirmative Action policies and procedures. Date is approximate
  - Tufts University Affirmative Action Plan, vol. I, 1974 -- 1975; UA057.002.001.00017 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Tufts University Affirmative Action Plan, vol. II, [1 of 3], 1974 -- 1975; UA057.002.001.00018 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Tufts University Affirmative Action Plan, vol. II [2 of 3], 1974 -- 1975; UA057.002.001.00019 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Tufts University Affirmative Action Plan, vol. II, [3 of 3], 1974 -- 1975; UA057.002.001.00020 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Tufts University Affirmative Action Plan, vol. III, [1 of 3], 1974 -- 1975; UA057.002.001.00021 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Tufts University Affirmative Action Plan, vol. III, [2 of 3], 1974 -- 1975; UA057.002.001.00022 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Tufts University Affirmative Action Plan, vol. III, [3 of 3], 1974 -- 1975; UA057.002.001.00023 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Tufts University Affirmative Action Plan, vol. IV, [1 of 3], 1974 -- 1975; UA057.002.001.00024 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Tufts University Affirmative Action Plan, vol. IV, [2 of 3], 1974 -- 1975; UA057.002.001.00025 (Box UA057 Shared 1)
  - Tufts University Affirmative Action Plan, vol. IV, [3 of 3], 1974 -- 1975; UA057.002.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Volume I, Tufts University, Review of Affirmative Action Progress (Index, Introduction, and Overall Analysis), 1978; UA057.002.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Volume II, Tufts University, Central Administration, Affirmative Action Plan, Workforce Analysis and Full Time Hiring Projection, 1978; UA057.002.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - Volume III, Tufts University, School of Dental Medicine, Affirmative Action Plan, Workforce Analysis and Full Time Hiring Projections, 1978; UA057.002.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - Volume IV, Tufts University, Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, Affirmative Action Plan, Workforce Analysis and Full Time Hiring Projections, 1978; UA057.002.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Volume V, Tufts University, School of Medicine, Affirmative Action Plan, Workforce Analysis and Full Time Hiring Projections, January 1978, UA057.002.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - Volume VI - Book A, Tufts University, Combined Arts and Sciences: Arts & Sciences Division and College of Engineering, Affirmative Action Plan, Workforce Analysis and Full Time Hiring Projections, 1978; UA057.002.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - Volume VI - Book B, Tufts University, Combined Arts and Sciences: College of Liberal Arts, Affirmative Action Plan, Workforce Analysis and Full Time Hiring Projections, 1978; UA057.002.002.00008 (Box 2)
  - Long Range Planning and Fundraising Objectives for Arts & Sciences over the next five years 1978-83 By Bernard W. Harleston, UA057.002.002.00009 (Box 2)
    CROSS REFERNCES: This report is cross listed with material in the records of the Department of Arts & Sciences in UA045/003.
  - Tufts University, Affirmative Action Plan,[1 of 3], 1981 -- 1982; UA057.002.002.00011 (Box 2)
  - Tufts University, Affirmative Action Plan, [2 of 3], 1981 -- 1982; UA057.002.002.00012 (Box 2)
  - Tufts University, Affirmative Action Plan, [3 of 3], 1981 -- 1982; UA057.002.002.00013 (Box 2)
  - Tufts University, Affirmative Action Plan, 1984 -- 1985; UA057.002.003.00001 (Box UA057 Shared 2)
  - Affirmative Action Program for Progress, 1971; UA057.002.004.00001 (Box 4)
    20 years from date of creation.
  - Affirmative Action Plan Revised, 1972; UA057.002.004.00002 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1975; UA057.002.004.00003 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan for Handicapped Persons, Disabled Veterans, and Veterans of the Vietnam Era, 1984 -- 1985; UA057.002.004.00004 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan [1 of 3], 1984 -- 1985; UA057.002.004.00005 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan [2 of 3], 1984 -- 1985; UA057.002.004.00006 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan [3 of 3], 1984 -- 1985; UA057.002.004.00007 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan [1 of 3], 1985 -- 1986; UA057.002.004.00008 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan [2 of 3], 1985 -- 1986; UA057.002.004.00009 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan [3 of 3], 1985 -- 1986; UA057.002.004.00010 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1987; UA057.002.004.00011 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1988; UA057.002.004.00012 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1990; UA057.002.004.00013 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1991; UA057.002.004.00014 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan for Handicapped Persons, Disabled Veterans, and Veterans of the Vietnam Era, 1992; UA057.002.004.00015 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1992; UA057.002.004.00016 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan Draft (Master Revision of Affirmative Action Plan 1993), 1993 -- 1994; UA057.002.004.00017 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan for Persons with Disabilities, Disabled Veterans, and Veterans of the Vietnam Era, 1993; UA057.002.004.00018 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan for Persons with Disabilities, Disabled Veterans, and Veterans of the Vietnam Era, 1994; UA057.002.004.00019 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan Draft, 1994; UA057.002.004.00020 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1994; UA057.002.005.00001 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Plan Draft, 1995; UA057.002.005.00002 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Plan for Persons with Disabilities, Disabled Veterans, and Veterans of the Vietnam Era, 1995; UA057.002.005.00003 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Plan Self-Assessment Corrections, 1995; UA057.002.005.00004 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Plan Draft, 1996; UA057.002.005.00005 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Plan Draft, 1996; UA057.002.005.00006 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1996; UA057.002.005.00007 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Policy for Applicants and Employees with Disabilities, 1997; UA057.002.005.00008 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1997; UA057.002.005.00009 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Plan for Persons with Disabilities, Disabled Veterans, and Veterans of the Vietnam Era, 1998; UA057.002.005.00010 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1998; UA057.002.005.00011 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1999; UA057.002.005.00012 (Box 5)
  - Utilization Analysis, 1999; UA057.002.005.00013 (Box 5)
  - AA Plan Text (Affirmative Action Plan 2000), UA057.002.005.00014 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Plan for Persons with Disabilities, Disabled Veterans, and Veterans of the Vietnam Era, 2000; UA057.002.005.00015 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Policy for Applicants and Employees with Disabilities, 2000; UA057.002.005.00016 (Box 5)
  - Statistics, 2000; UA057.002.005.00017 (Box 5)
  - AA Plan Text (Affirmative Action Plan Draft 2001), UA057.002.005.00018 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 2001; UA057.002.005.00019 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 2001; UA057.002.005.00020 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Plan for Persons with Disabilities, Disabled Veterans, and Veterans of the Vietnam Era, 2001; UA057.002.005.00021 (Box 5)
  - AA Plan Disability/Vet Yr. '00,'01,'02, 2000 -- 2002; UA057.002.005.00022 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 2002 -- 2003; UA057.002.005.00023 (Box 5)
  - Faculty and Staff Affirmative Action Plan, 2002 -- 2003; UA057.002.005.00024 (Box 5)
  - Fletcher Statistics, 2003; UA057.002.005.00025 (Box 5)
  - Faculty and Staff Affirmative Action Plan, 2004; UA057.002.005.00026 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 2004; UA057.002.005.00027 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 2006; UA057.002.005.00028 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Plan Summary, 2006; UA057.002.005.00029 (Box 5)
- Publications, 1970 -- 2007; 1983 -- 1998; UA057.003; 0.0 Linear Feet
  This series consists of publications created by the Office of Equal Opportunity and Affirmative Action. The pamphlets, booklets, and brochures cover Tufts University's policies regarding issues such as sexual harassment, affirmative action, and diversity.
  - [Publications], 1970 -- 1983; UA057.003.003.00002 (Box UA057 Shared 2)
  - [Publications], 1994 -- 1998; UA057.003.003.00003 (Box UA057 Shared 2)
  - [Publications], 2007; UA057.003.003.00004.000001 (Box UA057 Shared 2)
  - Policies and Procedures, 2012; UA057.003.003.00004.000002 (Box UA057 Shared 2)
- Additional accessions, 1970-2012; UA057.004
  - Program files, reports and plans, news clippings, 1970 -- 2012; UA057-001 (Box data_value_missing_9a6e5ada5c70e9395254099d7b5508c9, Box 1)
  - Tufts University: Stuff You Won't Find in the Fact Book, UA057-005